{  "questions": [
    {
      "question": "The expression: 'The greatest pride, or the greatest despondency, is the greatest ignorance of one's self' indicates the necessity of:",
      "options": [
        "compliance with measure",
        "self-respect",
        "self-education",
        "getting rid of prejudice",
        "self-restriction"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 4
    },
    {
      "question": "The position that some system of ethics applies for all similarly situated individuals, regardless of culture, race, religion, or any other distinguishing feature:",
      "options": [
        "moral absolutism",
        "moral universalism",
        "moral indulgence",
        "metaethical coherentism",
        "moral dogmatism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 1
    },
    {
      "question": "The act of matching attitudes, beliefs, and behaviors to group norms, politics or being like-minded in the result of subtle unconscious influences, or direct social pressure:",
      "options": [
        "cohesiveness",
        "non-conformism",
        "conformity",
        "obedience",
        "commonality"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 2
    },
    {
      "question": "The author of the dictum: 'True philosophy must start from the most immediate and comprehensive fact of consciousness, which says: 'I am life, which wills to live in the midst of life, which wills to live.'",
      "options": [
        "Albert Camus",
        "Albert The Great",
        "Albert Einstein",
        "Albert Schweitzer",
        "Albert Bandura"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 3
    },
    {
      "question": "According to J. Bentham and J.S. Mill, happiness is:",
      "options": [
        "freedom of choice",
        "pleasure and well-being",
        "the absence of pain and freedom of choice",
        "well-being",
        "pleasure and the lack of pain"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 4
    },
    {
      "question": "The author of the exclamation: 'Who is really close to you? Faithful friend, affectionate grandson, your descendant, great-grandson, and the land where you were born and raised!'",
      "options": [
        "Kazybek bi",
        "L.Gumilyov",
        "W. Shakespeare",
        "B. Franklin",
        "Socrates"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 0
    },
    {
      "question": "According to this conception, actions are good when they increase humanity's net happiness, creating more pleasure than they cause pain, and evil when they cause more pain than pleasure:",
      "options": [
        "hedonism",
        "utilitarianism",
        "stoicism",
        "epicureanism",
        "cynicism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 1
    },
    {
      "question": "A trait or quality that is deemed to be morally good and thus is valued as a foundation of good moral being:",
      "options": ["charity", "dignity", "virtue", "prudence", "justice"],
      "correct_answer": 2
    },
    {
      "question": "The English word 'ethics' is derived from the ancient Greek word ēthikós, meaning:",
      "options": [
        "compliance with the moral rules",
        "establishing moral order",
        "elimination of evil",
        "relating to one's character",
        "purposeful life"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 3
    },
    {
      "question": "An ethical view that all actions are inherently right or wrong, regardless of the purpose for which they are performed:",
      "options": [
        "moral dogmatism",
        "moral universalism",
        "moral relativism",
        "moral skepticism",
        "moral absolutism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 4
    },
    {
      "question": "The author of the dictum: 'It is impossible to think of anything at all in the world, or indeed even beyond it, that could be considered good without limitation except a good will.'",
      "options": [
        "I. Kant",
        "A. Schopenhauer",
        "Abay",
        "B. Spinoza",
        "A. Augustine"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 0
    },
    {
      "question": "“Nothing is morally right or wrong because there are no moral features in this world; thus, no moral judgments are true”:",
      "options": [
        "moral relativism",
        "moral nihilism",
        "moral objectivism",
        "moral ignorance",
        "moral eliminativism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 1
    },
    {
      "question": "Impartial and just treatment or behavior without favoritism or discrimination:",
      "options": [
        "rigidity",
        "straightforwardness",
        "fairness",
        "humbleness",
        "tolerance"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 2
    },
    {
      "question": "The normative ethical position that moral agents ought to act in their own self-interest:",
      "options": [
        "immorality",
        "rational egoism",
        "psychological egoism",
        "ethical egoism",
        "amorality"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 3
    },
    {
      "question": "The thought that 'ethics is nothing else than reverence for life' belongs to:",
      "options": [
        "Deni Diderot",
        "Leo Tolstoy",
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Korkyt Ata",
        "Albert Schweitzer"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 4
    },
    {
      "question": "This philosophy calls to accept what cannot be changed; to come to terms with existence and to endure in a rational way; to remain abstinence in the face of temptation:",
      "options": [
        "stoicism",
        "Epicureanism",
        "quietism",
        "quakerism",
        "providentialism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 0
    },
    {
      "question": "The principle that people get what they deserve with the interpretation of what then constitutes 'deserving' being impacted upon by numerous viewpoints in various fields, including concepts of moral correctness, rationality, law, religion, equality and fairness:",
      "options": ["tolerance", "justice", "sympathy", "empathy", "propensity"],
      "correct_answer": 1
    },
    {
      "question": "The ancient Greek root word êthos from which the word ēthikós ('ethics') comes, means:",
      "options": [
        "mannerliness",
        "manner",
        "character, moral nature",
        "civility",
        "courtesy"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 2
    },
    {
      "question": "A person who behaves in a way that is acceptable by most people and who avoids doing things that could be considered different or unusual:",
      "options": [
        "proponent",
        "follower",
        "supporter",
        "conformist",
        "adherent"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 3
    },
    {
      "question": "A view that philosophical anthropology and its concepts of 'human nature', 'man' or 'humanity' should be rejected as historically relative, ideological or metaphysical:",
      "options": [
        "transhumanism",
        "secularism",
        "radical humanism",
        "neohumanism",
        "anti-humanism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 4
    },
    {
      "question": "A class of meta-ethical theories in which all members entail that no one has any moral knowledge, more over it is impossible:",
      "options": [
        "moral skepticism",
        "moral nihilism",
        "moral absenteeism",
        "ethical realism",
        "agnosticism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 0
    },
    {
      "question": "“Postmodernity is best described as modernity without illusion, without the belief that humanity can be repaired by some ethic principle”:",
      "options": [
        "Jacques Derrida",
        "Zigmunt Bauman",
        "Richard Rorty",
        "Jean-François Lyotard",
        "Albert Camus"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 1
    },
    {
      "question": "A person who does not behave the way most people behave:",
      "options": [
        "remonstrant",
        "antagonist",
        "nonconformist",
        "opponent",
        "adversary"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 2
    },
    {
      "question": "A perspective on reality as a whole, a belief system, person's relation with what he accepts as being of ultimate importance:",
      "options": [
        "approach",
        "worldview",
        "life style",
        "life stance",
        "attitude"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 3
    },
    {
      "question": "Belief system or life stance that embraces human reason, secular ethics, while rejecting religious dogma, supernaturalism, and superstition as the basis of morality and decision making:",
      "options": [
        "naturalistic pantheism",
        "humanism",
        "atheism",
        "dogmatism",
        "secular humanism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": 4
    }
  ]
}
